Monmonier family papers, 1878-1968 (bulk 1885-1930).
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Monmonier family papers, 1878-1968 (bulk 1885-1930).
AZ 371
This collection consists of correspondence, financial records, photographs relating to the family and their businesses of store keeping, gas stations, and trailer courts. Legal papers, financial records, stockholders lists, assay reports, time books, and correspondence relate to the Flourine Mine and Milling Company, Leadville Mining Company, and others.
Monmonier family
5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
The Monmoniers were a pioneer family of Cochise County, Ariz. William Donalin Monmonier, and his son, Charles Swaney Monmonier were active in Tombstone and Pearce, Ariz. as Justices of the Peace, Notaries Public, members of the Pearce School Board, storekeepers, and Registrars of births and deaths.
Organization
This collection is organized into six series:
Series I: Papers of William D. Monmonier, 1878-1935
Series II: Papers of Charles S. Monmonier, 1916-1968
Series III: Mining Records, 1897-1965
Series IV: Records from Pearce, Ariz. and Cochise County, Ariz., 1896-1960
Series V: Knights of Pythias Records, 1899-1967
Series VI: Photographs
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of correspondence, financial records, photographs relating to the family and their businesses of store keeping, gas stations, and trailer courts. Legal papers, financial records, stockholders lists, assay reports, time books, and correspondence relate to the Flourine Mine and Milling Company, Leadville Mining Company, and others. Correspondence, reports, and cemetery records of the Knights of Pythias, Valley Lodge No. 21 are present. Cochise County Dist. 9 Justice Court proceedings, 1903 to 1908, and birth and death records, 1909-1939, are also present. Photographs are of Pearce mining and ranching operations, of Pearce and Tombstone residents, and of Monmonier family members.
Monmonier, William Donalin, 1849-1930 -- Archives; Monmonier, Charles Swaney, 1881-1975 -- Archives; Knights of Pythias. Valley Lodge No. 21 (Ariz.) -- Records and correspondence; Flourine Mining and Milling Company -- Records and correspondence; Leadville Mining Company -- Records and correspondence; Little Jessie Gold Mining Comapny; Arizona. Justice Court (Cochise County); Merchants -- Arizona -- Sources; Mines and mineral resources -- Arizona -- Cochise County -- History -- Sources; Justices of the peace -- Arizona -- Archives; Cochise County (Ariz.) -- Statistics, Vital; Pearce (Ariz.) -- History -- Sources; Correspondence; Photographs; Birth certificates; Death certificates
Separated Material
Postcards received with the collection were removed and cataloged separately. These include postcards from the 1909 Alaska-Yukon Exposition in Seattle, Wash. and postcards of Arizona.
Container List
- Series I: Papers of William D. Monmonier, 1878-1935
  - Personal Miscellany. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family Correspondence. 1903-1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence. 1878, 1899-1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notarial Record. November 1888-May 1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notarial Record. 1922-1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Account Book. 1911-1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Store Ledger, Tombstone, Ariz. 1893-1896 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Store Day Book, Tombstone, Ariz. 1896-1898 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Political Clippings. 1892-1894 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Court Cases. 1902-1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Speeches. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - William D. Monmonier Estate. 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hannah Monmonier Estate. 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Justice Court Record, Precinct No. 9, Cochise County, Arizona Territory. August 1903-July 1908 (Volume 2)
- Series II: Papers of Charles S. Monmonier, 1916-1968
  - Personal Miscellany (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Brother Julius W. Monmonier. 1916, 1943-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Brother Eustace Basil Monmonier. 1919, 1930-1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous Family. 1924-1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Wife Lucy with various family members. 1940-1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Mildred Richey. 1940 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: George H. Bott. 1953-1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Walter Newberry. 1951-1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Louis P. Waters. 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous. 1916-1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Notarial Record. 1931-1934 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Notarial Correspondence. 1930-1951 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Douglas Army Air Field, Douglas, Ariz. 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Automobiles. 1921-1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Insurance. 1930-1956 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Social Security. 1949-1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Various Cards: Identification, Memberships, Registration, etc. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Various compositions and reminiscences. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sketches and drawings. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Notarial Record. 1934-1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Various records from Sunnyside Auto Trailer Court and White Owl Trailer Court, Douglas, Arizona. 1947-1949 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gas Station Records. 1947-1949 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
  - Mortgages and Property. 1920-1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Taxes. 1923-1955 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Notes and memos. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous family biographical material. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series III: Mining Records, 1897-1965
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: Articles of Incorporation, By-Laws. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: Minutes of Meetings: Stockholders, Board of Directors, etc. 1905-1926 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: Stockholders lists, miscellaneous material. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: Stock Ledger. 1905-1923 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: Stock Certificate Record. 1905-1917 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: Stock Certificates. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: "First Ledger." 1905-1911 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: "Second Ledger." 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: Correspondence. 1906-1968 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: Notice of Mine Location. 1904-1909 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: Assay Reports. 1904-1924 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: Miscellaneous legal papers. 1906-1921 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: Miscellaneous financial papers, including taxes. 1909-1928 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Flourine Mining and Milling Company: Time Book. 1908-1911, 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Arizona Corporation Commission and Industrial Commission of Arizona. 1913-1929 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous material including notes, maps, brochure and photographs. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Leadville Mining Company: Correspondence. 1908-1949 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Leadville Mining Company: Stockholders lists, Minutes of Meetings, etc. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Leadville Mining Company: Assay, production and sales reports. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Leadville Mining Company: Miscellaneous financial records. 1906-1919 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Leadville Mining Company: Time Books, and miscellaneous accounts. 1905-1942 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Leadville Mining Company: Miscellaneous items including legal papers. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Little Jessie Gold Mining Company Minute Book. 1902-1908 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Moar Mine: Correspondence. 1897-1913 (Box 6, Folder 8a)
  - Moar Mine: Legal papers. 1899-1932 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Moar Mine: Financial papers. 1897-1910, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Holmes Copper Company. 1927-1935 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Holmes Mining Company. 1937 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Holmes-Western Consolidated Mines. 1941, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Pearce Mining Company operating the Commonwealth Mine. 1931-1941 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Courtland Copper Company Consolidated. 1913, 1943-1948 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Intermountain Mining & Engineering Company. 1942-1947 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Notices of Mine Locations. 1900-1953 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous mining correspondence. 1902-1946 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous mining items including papers relating to the Copper, Cochise and Eagle mining claims. 1904-1917 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Series IV: Records from Pearce, Ariz. and Cochise County, Ariz., 1896-1960
  - Population register. 1898-1916 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Birth and death records. 1909-1939 (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
  - Pearce Home Guard and Pearce Rifle Club, including photographs. 1912, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Pearce School: Minutes of Board Meetings and miscellaneous items. 1896-1938 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Pearce School: Correspondence. 1904-1909, 1932-1938, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Cochise County Farm Bureau roster and miscellaneous papers. 1921 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Monmonier Ranch papers and photographs. (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Series V: Knights of Pythias Records, 1899-1967
  - Valley Lodge No. 21: Correspondence. 1904-1961 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
  - Valley Lodge No. 21: Miscellaneous financial records. 1899-1930 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Valley Lodge No. 21: Miscellaneous material including Articles of Incorporation. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Valley Lodge No. 21 Cemetery: Correspondence. 1913-1967 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Valley Lodge No. 21 Cemetery: Map and grave record. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Valley Lodge No. 21 Cemetery: Miscellaneous financial records. 1916-1948 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Valley Lodge No. 21 Cemetery: Ledger. 1916-1966 (Box 8)
  - Valley Lodge No. 21: Semi-Annual Report. 1900-1908 (Volume 9)
  - Valley Lodge No. 21: Ledger. 1904-1917 (Volume 10)
- Series VI: Photographs
  - William D. Monmonier and wife. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Charles S. Monmonier. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Julius W. Monmonier and family. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Eustace Basil Monmonier and family. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - William D. "Bill" Monmonier and family. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Various Monmonier family. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Crouch family. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Blanke family. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Pearce, Ariz. including community activities and local persons. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 11, Folder 10)